<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Useful discoveries and practical observations, in some late remarkable cures of the scurvy. By E. Maynwaringe, Dr. in Physick.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217779</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829422</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1919:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Useful discoveries and practical observations, in some late remarkable cures of the scurvy. By E. Maynwaringe, Dr. in Physick.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 55 [i.e. 48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for T. Basset under St. Dunstans Church in Fleet-Sreet [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 48 misnumbered 55.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Diseases --  Causes and theories of causation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>USEFUL DISCOVERIES, AND PRACTICAL OBSERVATIONS, IN Some Late Remarkable Cures of the Scurvy.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E Maynwaringe,</hi> Dr. in Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Cognitio Sequitur Curaetiones.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der St. <hi>Dunſtans Church</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_diseased">
            <pb facs="tcp:33861:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33861:2"/>
            <head>To the Diſeaſed.</head>
            <p>IN vain it is to Diſcourſe, and have the Notion of Diſeaſes; unleſs alſo efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Medicines be found out to anſwer their Indications for Cure: Which to do, is the moſt difficult and laborious part of Phyſick. And this we may conclude from the often fruſtration and diſappointment of Medicines in their effects, after Learned Conſultations, and deliberate Determination of the Diſeaſe, Cauſes, Part affected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> rightly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Here is the great Check given to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians Learning; and, until this tryal of the Medicine, he receives no repulſe, but goes on ſmoothly with Applauſe and boldly: but, finding his Medicine take little or no effect for the purpoſe intended, is then at a ſtand a while: But, being loth to receive a baffle from the Diſeaſe, does preſcribe another, and perhaps another after that, a fourth and a fifth, and ſometimes many more if the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe be contumacious and ſtubborn: and this ſome will call a Methodical courſe of
<pb facs="tcp:33861:3"/>Phyſick. But I ſhall not harp upon that ſtring.</p>
            <p>This Diſappointment is too often obſerved in the practice of Phyſick, and this ariſing only from ineffectual, languid erroneous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and how does this come to paſs? but that the care and burthen of this work reſts upon thoſe that are unable and unfit to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it: or by truſting too much the credit of Authors and their traditional Medicines, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Galenical or Chymical; relying upon their authority, and the truth of their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which have deluded and fruſtrated the expectation of many. And this I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in practical Authors and Pharmaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paeas of both Sects, Medicines collected and borrowed from one another, and delivered thus from hand to hand, none knows who firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented them; or whether any of them ever made or tryed them, that highly extolls and gives large encomiums of their vertues.</p>
            <p>That many of theſe are Deluſions either in the proceſs, or the efficacy of the Medicine, to my own coſt and Labour, I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and muſt ſay with <hi>Helmont</hi> that great Philoſopher, <hi>Vexatio parit intellectum</hi> and therefore do Caution others, leſt they ſuffer upon this Rock: but he that will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to himſelf excelling Medicines (being accompliſhed with literature, with the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work
<pb facs="tcp:33861:3"/>and Canons of the Art,) let him not tye himſelf up, or credit too much this or that Author, but follow the dictates of his own reaſon, confirmed and guided by collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral experiments; and herein a Phyſician daily exerciſed, ſhall in time attain to great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſatisfaction in Medicine; and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to himſelf Medicaments of great worth and value: and this muſt be every Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans proper Labour and daily endeavours, that rationally intends, and rightly goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to improve and advance the efficacy and power of Medicines, that they may have their praiſe and fame in the World, and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician much ſatisfaction and content in their wonderful Operation. It is not, Sitting in his Study alone, and poring upon Books, but his own manual Operation and Inſpection over his Servants, that gives the great ſtroak to the buſineſs; the other does very litle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, but both, muſt needs do well: and I muſt ſay, and that juſtly, he that practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Phyſick, with a bare ſpeculative, trae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, and book-reading knowledg of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, is very unskilful in the true funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental knowledg of Medicines; and is as unfit to preſcribe or appoint Medicines in hazardous or difficult caſes, as the that by only reading of Navigation, is unable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and conduct a Ship to <hi>Eaſt-India.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33861:4"/>
            <p>And this is reaſon to averr: for he knows not what a Medicine is, nor can he give a good and certain account upon his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Nature of any Ingredient, but has all upon truſt: This or that man ſays it; the concluſion will not handſomly follow, <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is ſo. No wiſe man that can gain a certain knowledg of his own, will borrow at hazard of another; conſidering the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths and Erorrs that are ſcattered abroad in moſt Writings; that he which lives only by borrowing thus, ſhall run himſelf out of credit and Reputation in his Profeſſion, if blind Fortune be not very much his friend.</p>
            <p>'Tis moſt certain and true, that the Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of any Medicine are not known by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, but by their ſingle and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound preparation, and ſeparation of their conſtituent parts: and thus by handling, and Chymically diſſecting their bodies, each part lies bare, and preſents it ſelf to your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>And farther; An Ingredient whether of the Animal, Vegetable, or the Mineral Family, changeth its Nature and Effect, according to the variation of its Conſorts, with whom it is joyned: that it is not the ſame compounded with this, as it is with that; but works a different effect; becauſe many times they act upon each other, ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:33861:4"/>and moderating each others peculiar Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that a median nature does reſult: And therefore great care and knowledg in the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician is required, about the choice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Ingredients; that he be able to look through their ſeveral Natures, to find out their ſimilitude and repugnancy; their concord and diſcord: for hereby is known what properties will be advanced, and what depreſſed: and this an able Chymical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician can d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcern, as having a perſpective thorow knowledg, the other is but Exterior and Partial: and as the compoſition of Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients may alter and change their Natures; ſo likewiſe their various manner of Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſingly, do change an Ingredient, that it is made this or that, as a perite Artiſt pleaſeth, exalting, or proſtrating and killing this or that quality, as his purpoſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, I muſt take notice of the traditional and unprofitable account of Vegetables that our Herbals give; of which the Chymical Phyſician takes little notice, and is a ſmall aſſiſtance and guide to him in the Election of Plants for his ſeveral Intentions. Being ſatisfied long ſince that Medicament was the moſt weighty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of Phyſick, and that a defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency or error there, is a greater diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb facs="tcp:33861:5"/>and detriment to the Patient, then in the determination of the Deſeaſe; I did eagerly apply my ſelf to Medicines (according to the ancient cuſtom and general practice of the moſt learned and famous Phyſicians in all places; who were induſtrious Artiſts, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in preparing their own Medicines, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this later age) with as much curioſity as my knowledg could poſſibly direct. At firſt I was deſirous to make Experiments, and be fully informed in <hi>Galenic</hi> Medicines, being grounded upon thoſe Principles by my <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic Education,</hi> and was tenacious enough of that Doctrine, un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il a clearer proſpect of truth did appear, gained by Obſervations in practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Philoſophy, a ſerious ratiocination and ſtrict examination of Principles and received Opinions: but being removed off that Baſis, and confirmed by Chymical Tryals relating to Medicine; I deſerted the <hi>Galenic</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines as inferiour to that I diſcovered and was preſented to my view; and ever ſince have labored in Chemical Pharmacy, as being the moſt excellent way of preparing Medicines.</p>
            <p>Some Objections are made by the Learned, and by the Ignorant, againſt Chymical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; but to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndicate them from common ſlanders, and clearly to determine the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe and other Medicines, will take up more room than can be afforded in this
<pb facs="tcp:33861:5"/>place, and therefore muſt of neceſſity wave it, expecting an Opportunity hereafter, to venti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late that Subject: Only, by the way I muſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that Chymiſtry ſuffers much, and is eclipſed in its reputation by ſome illiterate pretenders and bold fellows, not qualified Philoſophical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but rudely intruding upon the Art, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due preparation and legitimate inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on brings ſcandal upon the learned, deſerving Profeſſors, and defamation to the Art, by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping the Title of Doctors and Chimical Phiſicians, that many are deceived by them, which are not able to diſcern the difference between a Doctor of Phyſick, and a crafty Empyric. But the ingenious Phyloſophical Artiſt, ought to be cheriſhed and incouraged in his Operations and rational Tryals.</p>
            <p>But to my purpoſe intended: in my Treatiſe of the Scurvy, having traced that Diſeaſe from its Infancy, and Generation, to its full groweth and ſtrength, its chief places of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, variety of appearance and monſtrous deformity; it remains, I ſhould now propoſe ſome effectual means to check and ſubdue the prevailing power of this ſpreading Diſeaſe, that daily growns, and encreaſeth to the ruine and decay of Nature; being poſſeſſed and ſeated in the Vital Principles, Seducing and Conſtraining them to enormity and defection from the regularity in which they were plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:33861:6"/>by Nature. And having ſtrictly ſurveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the condition and nature of this Diſeaſe, with its variety of attendants and additional ſtrength, being ready to joyn with any Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bific cauſe, and be transformed; I was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſit down here and reſt with a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative knowledg of this Diſeaſe, and leave the greateſt part of the work undone; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing and vanquiſhing of it by powerful Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: nor being willing to commit the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part to the industry and care of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for good reaſon) I have therefore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to form Medicinal Inſtruments to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Contumacious <hi>Herculean</hi> Diſeaſe: and as fit means for this encounter, I prepared three Medicines of a different Claſſis and Operation, to meet with the variety of Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, and Scorbutic Complications.</p>
            <p>In the Cure of the Scurvy, at leaſt in moſt Scorbutic caſes, there are three intentions of cure to be aimed at: the firſt is, Purgation or Cleanſing, to carry off that Scorbutic Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Degenerate Matter lodged in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and Bowels, de praving and alienating good food daily received: Secondly, robora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſtrengthning the digeſtive Faculties which are debilitated and alienated from the integrity of their Offices; not only the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtive Office of the Stomack, but the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Digeſtions alſo: Thirdly, Depuration
<pb facs="tcp:33861:6"/>of the Blood, and cleanſing the habit of the Body: Nature diſchargeth her ſelf from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſending daily to the exterior parts, thoſe alſo muſt be tainted more or leſs, as the Symptoms will manifeſt; and therefore do require to be freed from feculency, and the Blood purified.</p>
            <p>To anſwer theſe three Purpoſes, I prepared three Principal Medicines, <hi>viz.</hi> Scorbutic-Pills, Catholick-Elixir, and a Sudorific-Extract; Theſe Medicines I have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and improving alwoſt ſeven years, to advance their Efficacious,
<note place="margin">Dies diem docet.</note> but moſt gentle and benigne Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And, for the better effecting this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and aim the conſtant and daily uſe of them in divers Scorbutic perſons, attended with different Symptoms of the Diſeaſe, and complicated with divers other Diſeaſes, gives great information and ſatisfaction to me, in the ſeveral accounts I receive of their Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both at home, and abroad, by Letters from remote parts of this Kingdom: whereby I am taught, which way and wherein 'tis poſſible to improve them and to give them as great a Latitude of Univerſality and extent of Operation,
<note place="margin">Nihil eſt fimul &amp; inventum ac perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> in their peculiar Claſſes, as long experience and daily uſe, can dictate to their ſeveral repeated proceſſes and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als
<pb facs="tcp:33861:7"/>of making, and this is my Study and daily experience in Chymical tryals to improve theſe and all other Medicines I uſe in my Practice, that they may attain to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and energy, as <hi>Cito, tuto jucunde,</hi> to relieve the Diſeaſed, in the moſt contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Maladies, and deplorable Caſes, remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: hereby Medicines will gain greater eſteem, and the Art its deſerved repute and Fame, if Phyſicians by their own care and pains (as they ought) would manage this Work, and be as Induſtrious and skillful in this, as in the other parts of their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>But occaſions call me off from this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: I muſt haſten to finiſh the remainder, which is a more part cular account of the Operation of Medicines in the Cure of his Difeaſe; with ſome remarkable Obſervations in difficult Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and dubious Complications, I have met with lately in Practice, of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Conſideration to others in like manner Diſeaſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Clarken-well-Cloſe.</dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>E. M.</hi> Med. <hi>D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33861:7"/>
            <head>Of ſuch Purgation and proper Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, as is requiſite in Curing the <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PUrgation or Clenſing is praemitted as a regular and due courſe in the cure of moſt Diſeaſes; and it is inſtituted, chiefly to cleanſe the firſt region of the body, and to carry off what ſuperfluous or degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate matter is to be voided by the gutts: And this operation is neceſſary in the cure of moſt Diſeaſes, though ſeated in other parts; for, although the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity lye not in the firſt region of the body, neither in the Stomack, Gall, Gutts, Meſentery, Liver, nor Splene; yet 'tis aggravated, if thoſe parts be foul: and probably may be the original and foundation of thoſe remote Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, by conſent or tranſmiſſion; nor ſhall medicine carry its vertue without impediment and abatement, or food clearly conveyed to nouriſh the body; if
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33861:8"/>thoſe parts be foul, clogged and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</p>
            <p>Now to make choice of a fit and good Medicine, that will cleanſe the Stomack, Gutts, Meſentery, Liver, and Spleen, without offering injury to their peculiar Craſis or Ferments; that is, not to alienate them from their proper diſtinct natures, not to impreſs and ſtamp new qualities upon them; this is a Medicine you may freely uſe, and expect great relief from, in keeping the forenamed parts pure and clean; and ſuch a Medicine is to be uſed in the cure of ſcorbutic perſons: but if you uſe Purgers of a deleterious and virulent quality, that act <hi>per modum veneni;</hi> they will characteriſe their virulencies, and exotick adverſe properties upon the parts, alienate and debilitate the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their Functions and Offices; and the often uſe of them impairs Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture very much, though for the preſent ſometimes alleviation does acrue from the evacuation procured, though by bad means; and of this nature, are moſt of the Purgers in uſe, as <hi>Senna, Coloquin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tida, Rhuhab, Hellebore,</hi> &amp;c. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a laxative venom that ſtimulates Nature to expulſion.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33861:8"/>
            <p>Since Purgation is thus neceſſary, and purgatives ſo choiſely to be elected and choſen, not every medicine that cauſeth ſtools, but ſuch as is alſo endowed with balſamic and amicable properties, no way injurious to nature; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been a diligent Searcher and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover of ſuch a Medicine, that may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the intentions propoſed: and by degrees of improvement in ſome years time, by various alterations and tryals, have perfected a purgative vegetable Extract, that ſully ſatisfies and pleaſeth me, in its manner of operation and effects: and this Medicine is my Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Pills, ſo called, becauſe primely intended and contrived for the moſt effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious purgative medicine in all Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic Caſes. Now the Scurvy (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the former part of that Book) is complicated and joins with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſeaſes, Scorbutic Dropſies, Scorbutic Feavers, Aſthmaes, Palſies, Gouts, Scorbutic Conſumptions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that a particular medicine for this or that humor, being too narrow, and not adaequate to the latitude of the diſeaſe, will take no effect in many Scorbutic perſons: but ſuch as are radical and graduated in univerſality, are the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33861:9"/>and laudable medicines; I have therefore framed and improved this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to anſwer the intents of Purgation, in all Scorbutick perſons and caſes, and is the beſt purgative medicine, both in the manner of operation, and the effects, that ever I uſed, or read of.</p>
            <p>For farther ſatisfaction, and proof of this, I ſhall give you ſome brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of theſe Pills from my own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and obſervation, in divers ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon ſeveral of my Patients.</p>
            <p>They are effectually uſed againſt the defects and errors of digeſtion in the firſt, ſecond and third office: in the firſt, namely in all diſeaſes of the ſtomack re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring purgation and cleanſing down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the bad ſymptoms ariſing from thence; as Oppreſſion, Fulneſs, Nauſeating, Wind, Pain or Griping, Worms, loſs of Appetite; in all theſe caſes this medicine is very proper to cleanſe and diſcharge the ſtomack, make it clean and fit for the reception of wholeſom food, &amp; not till then can you expect good nouriſhment: if the ſtomack be ſoul, the nutriment conveyed from thence to ſupport and maintain the body, muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be vitiated and impure. And here I muſt relate to you what hapned to a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33861:9"/>Gentlewoman that had been long in a Scorbutic Atrophy (a Conſumption ariſing from the Scurvy) for ſome years, but not diſcovered; ſhe was obſerved to droop and decline, and her Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on change, and yet ſhe complained not of pain in any part; ſhe ſlept indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, but had little or no appetite to meat. Several conjectures there were concerning the cauſe of her langu ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Phyſicians, and others her Friends; ſome ſaid one thing, others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; try'd this medicine, then that; but all this while received no help: at laſt, ſhe applyed to me, and upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the whole matter, I found her to be Scorbutical: I gave my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her preſent ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how and from what cauſes procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and a Prognoſtick what whould follow if not prevented: whereupon ſhe willingly reſigned her ſelf to my care, and to do what I thought fit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore her.</p>
            <p>At firſt I appointed her to lay aſide her Dyet-drinks, Reſtaurative Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Potions (with which ſhe had been loaded again and again) and to reſt Ten dayes before I would give her any thing of Phyſick; in the interim to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33861:10"/>cat ſuch meat as her ſtomack did like and beſt agree with, which pleaſed her well, ſhe having been ſtrictly tyed up to a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: at Ten dayes end I gave her a Doſe of theſe Scorbute Pills, one over night, and two next morning, which workt ſix times very-gently with her that day; the night following ſhe ſlept well, and the next morning I appointed her to take a Doſe of my <hi>Catholic Elixir</hi> ſixteen drops in a ſpoonful of Sack, and likewiſe three mornings following, but increaſing two drops every morning: her ſtomack now was ſomething better, and ſhe more lively: The fifth day I ordered her a Doſe of the ſame Pills, which operated much as the former: and brought away two worms; fourdays following ſhe took the <hi>Elixir,</hi> and the fifth, a doſe of the Scorbute Pills; &amp; thus intermittingly ſhe uſed theſe two medicines for the ſpace of ſix weeks. At a fortnights end, her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack was much better both for appetite and digeſtion; at the months end ſhe was ſtronger and well able to go, very chearful, and eat her meat with delight; her Complexion altered much for the better, and about the ſixth week ſhe improved in fleſh, and began to be ſomething plump and full; then I bad
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33861:10"/>her deſiſt from her Pills, but continue the <hi>Elixir,</hi> which ſo ſtrengthened the digeſtive faculties, that ſhe daily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, grew ſtrong, and in a ſhort time obtained perfect health.</p>
            <p>To reflect upon this Story: Here was a latent Scorbutic Impurity that deaded the appetite, and what was forced down the ſtomack, did not digeſt, but degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; ſo that the body could not thrive, nor had the benefit of that little food re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; but this vitious matter being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off by a proper medicine, and the loaded tyred parts refreſhed and relieved by a generous ſpirituous Medicine; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then revives and returns to her wonted duties, with that ſtrength and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity as formerly. I might inſtance in many caſes parallel to this that I have met with in Scorbutic Patients; but I muſt be brief and proceed.</p>
            <p>Not only in Diſeaſes of the ſtomack, but alſo in the ſubſequent Digeſtions; I have found theſe Pills moſt effectually Abſterſive and Aperitive, opening Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the Liver and Spleen, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentery and Gutts; exonerating and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging thoſe parts of crude, coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, depraved fermenting matter, from whence ariſe pains and flatulent hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33861:11"/>of thoſe parts, Cachexies, or ill habits of body, Fluxes, Colicks, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chondriac Melancholy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and here I muſt relate the caſe of a Patient, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this place, worth your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was thus. A Gentleman, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged between Thirty and Forty, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtudious and melancholy, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of pain ſometimes in his left ſide under the ſhort Ribs, ſometimes in the other ſide oppoſite to it; ſometimes he was Coſtive, a ſtool once in two or three dayes; ſometimes Laxative, two or three ſtools in a day with ſome gripes and wind, his Belly often puffed up and diſtended, at which times he complained of a ſhortneſs of breath, ſtreightneſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Breaſt, and difficulty of breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like one that is Aſthmatick: in the night often afflicted with frightful dreams and Palpitations of the heart; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner (with other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which I omitt) he continued for the ſpace of four years or there abouts; all which time he was not negligent in procuring help, nor ſparing of his Purſe (having wherewith to do it) but apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf here and there for advice; ſome was of one opinion, another of a different judgment; and having tryed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33861:11"/>variety of medicines with little ſucceſs, was tyred, and reſolved to ſit down contented with his infirmities, and gave over Phyſick nere ſix months: But meeting with one, formerly a Patient of mine that I had cured, (though a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent caſe) encouraged him to come to me, or acquaint me by Letter firſt with his condition: whereupon he wrote to me (living at a great diſtance) and gave me a full Relation of his caſe, defiring my advice and aſſiſtance the ein, ſubmitting to what courſe I ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him: I conſidering the whole ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I was ſufficiently ſatisfied of the Diſeaſe, that he was deeply ſeiſed with the Scurvy, as the Syndrome and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of ſymptoms did certainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. Whereupon I ſent him my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Scurvy, to contemplate his Difeaſe at large, and to be uſeful to him as a Guide, with a Box of Scorbute Pills and an <hi>Elixir;</hi> and bad him proceed in the uſe of them according to Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which he did for Three weeks, then gave me an account, that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his Diſeaſe was much abated, the Symptoms more mild and eaſie, and not ſo frequent: thoſe nights he took a Pill, he ſlept more quietly then at other times;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33861:12"/>in his ſtools came away little lumps of a ſlimy jelly of a dark colour, or blackiſh, after which he was much at eaſe; his Belly and Hypochonders were more flat and ſoft; that ſince his Phyſick, ſome dark ſpots appeared in ſeveral parts of his body, with a moiſture upon his skin as enclining to ſweat ſome nights, but chiefly towards morning: This I liked well; and farther, appointed him the Sudoriſick Medicine hereafter mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to help forward and procure breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sweats twice in the week, which I judged to be of great advantage to him: this he diligently performed ſeven or eight times, until the ſpots vaniſhed; and then his ſpirits were more brisk and chearful, and more fit for buſineſs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thrown off that impure matter, and diſperſed the Cloud of Scorbutic vapours that clogged and darkned his ſpirits; his ſleep now was quiet, and (to be ſhort) the ſymptoms that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly moleſted him did not appear, but was reduced beyond expectation. I gave him ſome cautions and advice, leſt he might relapſe, which he punctually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and ſtood firm for ſeven or eight months after: Since, I hear nothing of him, but ſuppoſe him to be well,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33861:12"/>for which he was not ungrateful.</p>
            <p>I might Comment largely upon this caſe, and illuſtrate the Scurvy in the ſeveral Symptoms, though diſguiſed by various names uſually given, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the cauſes: but I paſs on.</p>
            <p>I have yet a farther Account of theſe Pills, how, and in what principal Caſes I have uſed them ſucceſsfully; for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and infirmities of the Head, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted though ariſing from inferior parts moſt often; as Apoplexy, Epilepſies, Convulſion, Palſies, Vertigoes, Sopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riferous and drowſy Infirmities, Rheums, Head-aches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Medicine is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably uſed, by Eradicating their cauſes, that require Abſterſion and Evacuation in the lower Regions of the Body. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes aſcribed to the Head, though ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing there, yet for the moſt part do ariſe from inferiour parts, occaſioned by their Impurities, Obſtructions, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; for one that is Idiopathically Afflicted, ten are Sympathically affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by conſent of parts, and tranſmiſſion of ſome Morbifick matter thither: the Diſeaſe appears in one part, but the foundation and cauſe is Radicated in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and to that part muſt the cure be directed.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33861:13"/>
            <p>And therefore, if well obſerved, we frequently meet with Scorbutic Palſies, Scorbutick Convulſions Apoplexies, Slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Diſeaſes, pains of the head Giddineſs, trembling of the Nervs, Deafneſs, dull Sight and Blindneſs; and all theſe ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Scurvy or Scorbutick im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity of the body oftentimes, and theſe are not cured but by Anti-ſcorbutic Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; and thoſe that endeavour other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with their Specificks and appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Medicines, to the parts where ſuch Symptoms and Diſeaſes do appear, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain, and are fruſtrated in their intended Cures.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance in many more caſes wherein this Medicine hath done me good ſervice, but that would be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to relate: therefore in general I muſt ſay, for Sorbutic perſons, and the various Symptoms that attend that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, whether in this part, or that part; theſe Pills are the beſt Abſterſive and Purgative Medicine I ever made uſe of, being ſo amicable and friendly to nature, in their Operation, performing with ſo much eaſe and gentleneſs, that I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to the weakeſt bodies with good ſucceſs, proportioning the doſe according to the ability of the body.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33861:13"/>
            <p>I ſhall here ſet down the Doſe and Circumſtances that belong to the taking of theſe Pills.</p>
            <p>The ordinary Doſe for man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is three Pills; ſome Bodies (though very ſeldom) require four: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times two Pills is ſufficient, for weak bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſuch as work freely with a ſmall matter.</p>
            <p>So much difference there is in bodies for purging, that two of theſe Pills are ſufficient for ſome; but moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three Pills are required, ſeldom four: therefore try your body firſt, with a leſſer Doſe then, if it require more, you may add to the next; and in ſo doing you will not err: For example, If you have a ſtubborn body, difficult and hard to purge, and the firſt Doſe works but little,
<note place="margin">Tutius eſt peccare in defectu, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in exceſſu.</note> the next Doſe you may take one Pill more: but if you have a lax gentle body freer in Operation than you expected, then abate a Pill, if the firſt work too nimbly with you. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of bodies is ſuch in Operation, (eſpecially purging) that they require a different Doſe, or quantity for their proportion, which cannot ſo exactly be determined and appointed by the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33861:14"/>of the moſt skilful Phyſician, but by a rational Conjecture; untill the firſt experiment and tryal of their bodies, (which uncertainty, is not in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, but in the diverſity of bodies); and after the firſt Doſe taken, your own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then, conſidering the condition of your body with the former, will prompt you in the next, whether to keep to the ſame, to augment, or abate.
<note n="*" place="margin">Solutiva enim fortia cum ſuccis texuperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ibus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem.</note> And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this as a neceſſary cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you covet not ſtrong Purges and large Evacuations, to have many ſtools in a day (a common error) which offers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to Nature, and force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſweeping down both good and bad together;
<note n="*" place="margin">Eradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuatio op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timè per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plures per ſicitur eva cuationes minorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas.</note> but rather chooſe to draw away the offending matter gently by degrees, giving Nature time for ſeparation, the pure from the impure and noxious: four or five Stools in a day is ſufficient, but not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed ſix; and that number I intend you to aim at and no more; and thus doing, you will find Phyſick much more beneficial, nature
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33861:14"/>more kindly aſſiſting, and not at all weakned.</p>
            <p>Some there are, who, unleſs their Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick work half a ſcore or a dozen times, think they have kept Houſe for nothing, and their Money caſt away, accounting the goodneſs of their Phyſick by the number of Stools; but they deceive themſelves very much in deſiring ſtrong Purgations, which weaken and impair Nature, and thereby you protract your Cure and not haſten it.</p>
            <p>Concerning preparation before Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, much talked of; take this Advice: that ſoluble bodies, readily yeilding obedience to gentle Purging Medicines, need no other preparation than what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath provided in the diſpoſition of their own bodies; but for thoſe bodies that are more hot, dry, coſtive and very ſtubborn in Operation, it will be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to facilitate their Purgation, by eating ſtewed prunes, water grewel, or barley broth with raiſins and currants, or by drinking whey, or ſider, two or three daies before, which will prepare, moiſten, cool, and open your body, and make it more ſoluble and eaſy in purging.</p>
            <p>The times for taking theſe Pills ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33861:15"/>is thus, (except good reaſon, in ſome bodies, perſwade the contrary:) Take one Pill over night going to bed, having eaten but a light Supper at ſix of the clock before; the next morning early in bed, take the remaining part of the Doſe; and you may ſleep an hour after if you be diſpoſed, but not longer; nor like long in bed after, leſt you check the Operation of the Medicine, and thereby cauſe you to be ſickiſh at Stomack in your riſing: when you are up, drink a little warm poſſet-drink, made of ſmall bear, or ſmall Ale, or thin broth for this purpoſe, and forbear eating until noon: but although theſe Pills are appointed to be taken, one over night, the other in the morning; yet if you find any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience thereby, you may take the whole Doſe in the morning very early, and lie two hours after: But if you have not a juſt cauſe for alteration obſerve the Preſcription.</p>
            <p>Theſe Pills take thus every fourth or fifth day, and you will find it beſt to give ſuch intermiſſion: Chronick or old Diſeaſes muſt have time to be Eradicated, and you muſt reduce nature from an ill
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33861:15"/>habit by degrees,
<note n="*" place="margin">Semper expedit paulatim ducere quàm ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitò.</note> better than haſtily; As diſeaſes come on, gradually prevailing upon and ſeducing nature from her Integrity; ſo nature by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, muſt be brought off and reſtored again to her power and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Cum natura malè ſuſtinet repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinas mutationes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For going abroad after your Pills that day, if you deſire it, or occaſions require, take this advice; if your body be indifferent ſtrong, not apt upon ſmall occaſions to take cold, the ſeaſon tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and fair weather, having moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Doſe of your Pills, ſo as to work but three, or four times at moſt; you may then go abroad without prejudice: but if it fall out to be otherwiſe, then it is better to keep in, that day.</p>
            <p>If any ask, At what times of the year theſe Pills are to be taken; I anſwer, you may ſafely and with benefit, at any time of the year, provided you order your ſelf ſuitable to the ſeaſon; that is, in Winter-weather, a warm Chamber and good fire; in Summer-hot weather, a cool Room free from the Sun; be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in Cloathing, and gentle in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to heat your ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33861:16"/>
            <p>For the Mornings in the midſt of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, they are temperate and fit for Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and the Operation will be done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the heat of the day; ſo that in this temperate Climate, you may take Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick (with diſcretion) at any ſeaſon of the year, the Dog-daies not excepted, although it is an opinion among the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, that that time is dangerous; but that is a vulgar error, eaſy to be refuted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Reſtoring and Rectifying the Digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neceſſary in Curing the <hi>SCURVY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the preceding Diſcourſe of that Treatiſe where the Scurvy is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted and laid open in the cauſes and manner of Generation; you find it plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Radicated in the Digeſtions, or Digeſtive Offices; by whoſe Aberrations from Integrity, and fruſtrations of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their Duties as they ought, this Diſeaſe is begotten: in the Cure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we muſt have an eye to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in Vigour, and Deviation from the Rectitude and manner of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance being Alienated and Deprav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33861:16"/>
            <p>The former Medicine <hi>viz.</hi> the Scorbute-Pills was deſigned, to cleanſe and carry off the Producted Scorbutick matter; another Medicine alſo muſt neceſſarily be invented to Roborate and ſtrengthen the Faculties, to reſtore and confirm them in the performance of their Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or elſe the like Scorbutick matter will be generated again, and nature will ſoon relapſe into the Former ſtate; In vain it is to pump, except you ſtop the Leak; Purging, carries off the Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate matter, and does a neceſſary work; but that does not Vigorate, re-inforce and give new ſtrength to the Digeſtive Faculties, that were tyred and alienated in their Principles: that muſt be done by another Medicine, whoſe property is to excite, unite and joyn with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal agent in each faculty.</p>
            <p>To make this more plain and eaſie to be apprehended by indifferent Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; firſt I ſhall ſhew you how nature does perform her daily work; Then I ſhall ſhew, how ſhe declines and falls off; and Thirdly, I ſhall manifeſt how ſhe is to be aſſiſted and reſtored.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as food is received into the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, nature preſently falls about her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to digeſt, to diſſolve, &amp; ſeparate the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33861:17"/>parts of it, to volatiſe, to diſtribute and tranſmit from one digeſtive office to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, to ſequeſter and throw aſide the unprofitable and excrementitious part, to attract and ſuck in the alimentary, to refine and alter it by ſeveral elaborati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to extract and draw out the pure ſpirituous part for ſupply of ſpirits, the reſt aſſimilated into the humoral and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid parts; from hence the body is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and maintained in ſtrength and vigour: and this is Natural Chymiſtry, performed every day in mans body in the regular courſe of nature; but when nature declines and fails in the ordinary and daily work of her own preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether by intemperance, improper food, irregular and injurious cuſtomes or accidents, or Spontaneoſly from an Imbecile Radication of principles, and bad Craſis of parts; the body then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes apace, when the principle functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are weakly and depravedly exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; neceſſarily then an Auxiliary means and Aſſiſtant muſt be applyed to reſtore nature to her ſtrength and regular courſe again; ſomething that muſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and vigorate nature, that muſt excite and cooperate in Conjunction with the movent principle; that as a new Spring,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33861:17"/>will give power and force to the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Conſidering this ſo neceſſary and uſeful in the cure of moſt Infirmities, as alſo to eſtabliſh and confirm a Cure wrought from Recidivation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe; I thought it a principal work to find out and form ſuch a medicine as may anſwer the intentions propoſed, and therefore have by ſeveral tryals and improvements effected and wrought ſuch a medicine to that degree and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent power, as is very efficacious in the deficienties and enervation of the dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive faculties, to Reſtore and Roborate them in their functions; which medicine is called, and known by the name of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelic Elixir</hi> (now altered and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved)</p>
            <p>And this was the cuſtom and manner of the ancient and moſt famous Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to acquire by their proper labour and ſedulous induſtry, ſome great <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana</hi>'s, ſecret and choiſe medicines of excelling vertue, which they eſteemed as a treaſure, and gave them peculiar names to be diſtinguiſhed and known by: and that ſuch medicines might be known to the world, for the good and benefit of the Diſeaſed; they did publiſh their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, as <hi>Angelus Sala</hi> in the Preface to his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33861:18"/>Precious Antidote, does apologize for himſelf in doing the like: <hi>Etiam magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominis medicis ſolenne olim fuit, medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti alicujus particularis virtutes, quas quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> accurata obſervatione annotaverat peculiari quodum tractatu literis conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare.</hi> Oper: Med: Chym. pag. 420. ſayes he, It has been the ancient cuſtom of Phyſicians, &amp; thoſe men of great fame, to write a Treatiſe of the vertues of ſome particular medicine, which they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſtrict obſervation; then he extols the efficacy and worth of his medicine, and excuſes the concealment of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Helmont</hi> alſo, that great Philoſopher and Phyſician, had his private medicines which he highly valued; ſo alſo in the Writings of the moſt Eminent Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we find they had their <hi>Arcana</hi>'s, ſecret medicines which they would not diſcover, ſave only their vertues and manner of uſe; therefore I may ſay as <hi>Angelus Sala, Quod ſi illis hoc vitio non fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it datum, neque mihi, qui eorum ad exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum.</hi>—</p>
            <p>But ſince the late faſhion of Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing came up in uſe, ſome ignorant buzzards which I could name, that have objected this againſt me, (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33861:18"/>of our own Faculty) think this an empirical way; but therein they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their ignorance, not knowing the ancient and moſt legitimate way of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and what is the whole duty of a Phyſician: See what Famous <hi>Quercetan</hi> ſayes upon the Queſtion, <hi>An medicum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Quer: Rediviv:</hi> pag. 218. Whether a Phyſician ought to make medicines; He will tell you, you are <hi>Pſeudomedicus,</hi> a Counterfeit Phyſician, if you do not make medicines. Pray look there, and then you will ſay, 'tis a ſhame for a Phyſician not to be expert in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king medicines.</p>
            <p>As a duty, and following the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the moſt Eminent Phyſicians. I have been and am a conſtant labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>in Pharmacy,</hi> thereby to acquire and purchaſe the choiſeſt Medicines that Art and pains can procure; and by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al making, and altering upon tryals, I have purchaſed as noble Medicines I think, as any man can procure; not but that other Phyſicians that have been thus diligent in Preparation of Medicines, as I have been, may have as good; but without this Labour and Induſtry, no man can be maſter of ſuch. In particular, the forenamed <hi>Elixir,</hi> as it is now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33861:19"/>and advanced, I have a great eſteem for, and is a great aſſiſtant to the Stomack in the office of Digeſtion, for it mainly fortifies and roborates that Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that the bad effects of a weak or depraved Digeſtion, are notably Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and amended; as crudity and indigeſtion, flatulency or winde, Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiouſneſs or Vomiting, Fulneſs or Opreſſion, Loſs of Appetite, Eructati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Belching; and this it performs by aſiſting the Stomack's Digeſtive Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being deficient and decayed by Age, Intemperance, Incongruous Dyet, Diſorder, or Natural Infirmities.</p>
            <p>One Caſe amongſt the reſt, relating hither, I well remember, which I think good to relate: A woman that had been troubled with the Scurvy for ſome years though ſcarce taken notice of, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be from other cauſes, what ſymptoms did appear; amongſt the reſt, for ſome time ſhe was moleſted, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a morning with a drineſs in her mouth, and an ill taſte; afterwards her ſtomack would nauſeate ſometimes, and ſoon after did begin to vomit: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe took ſeveral medicines to ſtay vomiting, and to ſtrengthen the ſtomack, but all in vain, and rather aggravated
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33861:19"/>her Griefs, ſtraining to Vomit with more violence, and little or nothing came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: when I was made acquainted with it, and underſtanding the Symptoms to ariſe from the Scurvy; upon examination of the whole matter, I ſent her this <hi>Elixir</hi> with directions; and at the third or fourth Doſe, her Vomiting and nauſeating was gone, and much at eaſe: then I appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her the Scorbute-Pills, to be uſed inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittingly with this <hi>Elixir</hi> for ſome time; and ſoon after, the other Scorbune Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms which moleſted her, vaniſhed, and ſhe regained her former health: Whereby you may obſerve that the Scurvy will not be tamed but by Anti-ſcorbutic Medicines: and although ſome Symptoms of the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy be common and like with thoſe from other diſeaſes, whereby many are deceived in their cauſes; yet, if they ariſe from a Scorbutic Root, they will not be cure but by Anti-ſcorbutic Medicines; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whar Symptoms of Sickneſs do appear in any perſon, ought ſtrictly and nicely to be examined by a diſcerning judgment, to know the right ſpring and foundation of their Riſe.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, Not only the Stomack and firſt Digeſtion is benefited and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this <hi>Elixir,</hi> but the ſubſequent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33861:20"/>are promoted, and their defects corrected hereby; and this Medicine I uſe ſucceſsfully againſt many Infirmities ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Meſentery, Guts, Liver, or Spleen; as when they are languid and weak, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating and falling off from their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are obſtructed with crude depraved Matter; wanting Spirit and Vigour, and acuteneſs of Ferment fit for their proper works; from whence Hypocondriack Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, Stitches, Pains, Tumors, and flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſtenſions of the Hypoconders and Belly: In ſuch caſes, this Medicine pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates atteneates opens, and diſcuſſeth, ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borates and gives great relief; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for Melancholy drooping Spirits, and Palpitations of the Heart, Anguſtneſs and Compreſſion about that Region, ariſing from a Scorbutic Feculency and Impurity; an ill-affected Spleen, or Matrix, from whence Vapours do aſſurge to afflict the heart and vital Spirit; this <hi>Elixir</hi> is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per help, and alſo effectual in Scorbutic Aſthmaes, difficult and ſhort Breathing, Coughs and Scorbutic Conſumptions. But of theſe you may read at large, in my Treatiſe <hi>of Conſumptions,</hi> and I have there appropriated two excellent and highly graduated Medicines for Conſumptive perſons; a Reſtaurative Eſſence, and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamic
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33861:20"/>Extract, with which I have recovered ſome, beyond expectation.</p>
            <p>That you may be the more cautious in examining the Symptoms of Diſeaſes, what foundation they have, and whence they do proceed, that you may not labour in vain for a cure; I have noted a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Caſe in a Patient of mine, worth your Obſervation, which was thus: A young man about thirty years of Age, a Student and tenderly bred, was ſubject to ſhort and difficult breathing, but without a Cough, or very little; he was adviſed to many Pectoral Medicines to open and ſtrengthen the Lungs, which he uſed, but with little effect: his Diſeaſe by time increaſed upon him, and he was troubled with palpitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Heart, and ſtoppage of Breath, in his Sleep, that he was affraid of Suffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; he then unhappily fell into the hands of an Emperick, who purged him with violent Medicines ſo, that he began to be Hydropical, did puff up, and limbs Swell, nor did the other Symptoms abate. After this and other paſſages (too long to relate) I was ſent for, and examined the Patient; found his complaint was chiefly under the Diaphgrama toward the Orifice of the Stomack, that his Lungs were good, and the Cauſe of his ſhort and difficult
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33861:21"/>breathing was not in the Breaſt, but by Compreſſion of the Diaphragma, from a turgid aeſtuation of Scorbutic matter, which threatned Suffocation ſometimes: (And upon this very cauſe, I knew a very Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctor of Phyſick, that died ſuddainly in his bed): I peruſed and made inſpection into the Urine, and examined his Pulſe, as now and formerly; both which conſented to, and confirmed the Scurvy: Then I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, what Medicines had been given him; and thoſe were moſt Pectoral, except ſome churliſh Purges, after which he was much worſe, and began to ſwell; and now he was about to take a Dyet-drink for the Dropſy, which was like to prove as the reſt: but the Patient committing himſelf into my hands, I bad him deſiſt from all Medicines but what I appointed; and firſt I gave him this <hi>Elixir</hi> (he being very weak) which as a Cordial did revive him, and after a few daies was much altered for the better, and ſlept more quietly, with a greater freedom in breathing: he continued this alone, for ten dayes; in which time he gained ſtrength and had a ſtomack to his meat: then I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected him the uſe of the Scorbute-Pills, which abated the ſwelling of his Limbs at twice taking, and proceeded in the uſe of theſe two Medicines. Laſtly, I appointed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33861:21"/>him the Sudorific Medicine hereafter men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; and in a ſhort time, he was reduced by this courſe to good health and free from his former Complaints. By the whole Story you may obſerve, Firſt, that the Scurvy is diſguiſed, and appears in the ſhape of other Diſeaſes. Secondly, that thoſe Diſeaſes ſo counterfeited, are not cured but by Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Medicines which are Anti-ſcorbutic: and therefore it much concerns the Sick, that their Diſeaſes be rightly ſtated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by one that can make a true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Diſcovery; and not according to external Appearance, and common Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, which is very Fallacious.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to let you know farther, How and wherein this <hi>Elixir</hi> is uſeful to me in Practice; and that in ſuddain emergent caſes of fainting: as alſo in Languiſhing Diſeaſes, and Caſes of Extremity when the Patient is ſpent and brought ſo low that no Phyſick can be Adminiſtred; this, as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and ſupport to the Languiſhing decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Faculties, may daily be exhibited; and this I have frequently proved: particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a Perſon of Honour, given over by his Phyſicians, being ſpent and decayed and highly ſwoln in a Scorbutic Aſthma and Dropſy, was gaſping for breath, when I came to him; but exhibiting this <hi>Elixir,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33861:22"/>he did wonderfully revive, and his difficult &amp; ſhort breathing was much enlarged and eaſed for a few daies, for which he did Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol the Medicine: but, being paſt the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Recovery, and incapable of other Medicines, requiſite or Cure, he dyed.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object: This poſſibly may be a good Medicine in deſperate Caſes, and approaches of Death; but how can it be proper and fit for a man that can eat his meat well, and walk abroad, only inclining to the Scurvy, and ſome ſmall Impediments from thence? I anſwer: That Medicine which is endowed with ſo much Vertue, to bring relief to a decayed or dying man; muſt needs be of great power and efficacy, to give Vigour and ſtrength to all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: Now Scorbutic Infirmities, or impedimens of what ſort ſoever, do ariſe from the Imbecillity, Aberration, or Declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome Faculty in the Body, injured or decayed which requires a generous and noble Medicine to Rectifie and Vigorate, (at leaſt, it will better be performed by ſuch) not a languid dull Medicine; and therefore this Objection is vain; for the greater power a Medicine hath, the more likely and better to do the buſineſs be it little or much: and therefore if your Caſe require help, do it by an acute Vigorous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33861:22"/>Medicine, and you may expect your Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities to be removed, <hi>Citiùs tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iùs jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diùs,</hi> in a ſhorter time, with more ſafety and certainty, with leſs diſguſt in taking or trouble in Operation.</p>
            <p>Now the main Scope and Intention of this Medicine, is, to relieve the Spirits Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed or Exhauſted, to Diſcuſs Flatulent Vapours, to open Obſtructions, and to Rectifie and Roborate the Digeſtive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, from whence Scorbutic Symptoms do ariſe; and ſuch a Medicine is neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in the cure of the Scurvy, and its Complicated effects.</p>
            <p>I have briefly ſhewed you the power and properties belonging to an Anti-ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butic Medicine, requiſite to be uſed in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scurvy: ſuch a Medicine I ſay is required; tis not Purging alone will do it, but other Operations muſt joyn to effect the purpoſe. For advice and rules to thoſe that uſe this Catholick <hi>Elixir</hi> (living farr diſtant from me) that they may not Erre in the taking of it, let them obſerve as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>That in the uſe of this <hi>Elixir</hi> with the Scorbute-Pills, it is beſt to begin with the Pills; except the perſon be very weak, or ſpent, and firſt require ſome ſtrengthning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33861:23"/>and reviving Medicine, then you may firſt begin with the <hi>Elixir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo that this <hi>Elixir</hi> is not to be taken thoſe daies you Purge, but every Intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting day between Purging.</p>
            <p>That this <hi>Elixir</hi> is not to be taken or taſted alone but mixt with ſome good Liquor, and that ought to be the beſt Canary; for bad Wine alters and abates the Virtue of the Medecine. It may be taken in French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, if the Patient cannot agreee with Sack.</p>
            <p>The Doſe for man or woman, is thirty drops: for ten years old, twenty drops; for five years, ten drops.</p>
            <p>And obſerve this; that at the firſt taking you begin but with half the Doſe that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for your age; as thus: thirty drops is appointed for a man, let him begin with fifteen or ſixteen drops, and then augment two or three drops every day after, until he aſcend to thirty, and then there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue that Doſe afterwards.</p>
            <p>Take it (in Bed if you be weak) in a ſpoonful of Sack, every morning, faſting an hour and half after; and at five of the Clock After-noon; but you are not ſo ſtrictly to obſerve the after-noons, but, if that your occaſions do not well permit (as when you muſt be abroad or the like,) you may omit.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33861:23"/>
            <p>In keeping this <hi>Elixir,</hi> let it be well ſtopt; for dropping of it exactly, a Cruet is beſt. Some may ask, What time of the year this Medicine may, or may not be uſed; I anſwer, No time of the year for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the uſe of it; but it is profitably taken at any ſeaſon of the year: nor may wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men forbear the uſe of it at ſuch times of the month, when all other Phyſick is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden; but is helpful to Nature at ſuch a time, in procuring them with more eaſe and freedom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Curing the Scurvy by Tranſpiration, and the neceſſary uſe of a good Sudorific Medicine.</head>
            <p>THe Scurvy is not a particular Diſeaſe limited to this or that part of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but extends it ſelf throughout the whole as appears by the variety of Symptoms, in ſeveral parts of the Body; and being of this extent, Medicine alſo muſt have the ſame Latitude of Operation to proſecute and reach into its utmoſt and fartheſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Purgation that cleanſeth the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral and more inward parts, as the Stomack, Guts, Meſentery, Liver and Spleen: Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration that reſpects chiefly the habit of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33861:24"/>the Body and external parts, purifying the Maſs of Blood, and vital ſtreams.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Operations are neceſſary for Cure in moſt Scorbutic caſes, as the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſes and obſervations in Practice recited, does manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Some there are that deceive themſelves, and lay the whole ſtreſs of the Cure upon Purging, and that they proſecute very often (and it were well if the purgatives be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) but the effects may inform and tell them, that there is ſomething elſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite; and they find it ſo. The Scurvy is not ſo eaſily diſlodged and thrown out by a ſingle Operation of Medicine; but requires rectifying and ſtrengthning of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtive Faculties alſo, and depuration of the Blood.</p>
            <p>The Body of man is perſpirable, and in his due ſtate of health continually more or leſs doth tranſpire and breath out humid vapours and a ſuperfluous moiſture by the Pores of the Body; hereby the Maſs of Blood and habit of the Body is cleanſed and diſcharged of that which is ſuperfluous or impure and unfit to be retained; and this inſenſible Evacuation is ſo requiſite, that without tranſpiration the Maſs of Blood cannot be depurated, but remains muddy and defiled, which forceth Nature to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33861:24"/>fermentation and morbific Erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Proper and amicable Purgation doth well, acts a good part, and ought to be prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in moſt caſes, which alone do check a Diſeaſe and leſſen it, by carrying off a I morbific matter in the lower Region of the Body; but if the Maſs of Blood, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of the Body be tainted and corrupted, the vital ſtream and thoſe parts irrigated and fed from thence, are not purified as they ought, but by Exſudation and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; and the Spirits that are clogg'd and infeſted by impure matter, which dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens their light, cauſing Melancholy and indiſpoſed heavineſs, are hereby relieved and unfettered, become brisk, aery, and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as before.</p>
            <p>And in promoting this Operation we imitate and aſſiſt Nature which continually does <hi>Emittere &amp; Tranſpirare per Poros,</hi> at leaſt ought ſo to breathe forth ſuperfluous vapours and humidity, and when this is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and reſtrained, by occluſion and ſhutting up the pores by cold or otherwiſe; or Nature unable thus to relieve and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge her ſelf by reaſon of debility and inſufficiency in ſeparating and protruding; it is not long but ſome Diſeaſe, or many, ariſeth from the courſe of Nature thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited: either a ſudden febril aeſtuation;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33861:25"/>or erratic pains in this or that part; or a ſlow eruption of groſſer matter ſticking in the skin diſcolouring and ſpotting of it; or bringing forth Scurf, Puſtules, or other Extretions.</p>
            <p>By this you may underſtand the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that doth ariſe by the regular courſe of Nature in her daily Operations and Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the profitable aſſiſtance of Art in promoting them when impeded, as alſo the prejudice and damage by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall relate to you the Caſe of a Scorbutick Patient, pertinent to the proceeding Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>A Gentlewoman, aged between Forty and Fifty, formerly fatt and fleſhy, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a lean ſtate; being troubled for ſome years with a laſſitude or wearineſs in her Limbs, and Indiſpoſition to Action, and with pains at ſome times: afterwards in <hi>Autumn,</hi> a weakneſs and numbneſs poſſeſſed her Limbs, that diſabled her in going: All this while ſhe was not negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to ſeek for help, had ſuch Advice as the Country did afford, and uſed many Medicines; but her Diſeaſe prevailed ſtill, each <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Autumn</hi> being worſe than the former: it hapned that a Relation of her caſe was ſent to me, (ſhe living a great
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33861:25"/>diſtance from <hi>London</hi>) what was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the firſt Relation, I interrogated in my Anſwer, and the next Account I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, did fully ſatisfie me: I found the Scurvy diſguiſed to act in ſeveral Scenes, after a different manner: the Medicines ſhe had uſed were proper for the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms that did appear, barely conſidered; but not as they had a Relation and were grounded upon the Scurvy, which being undiſcerned did fruſtrate all the Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for Cure: Letting of her blood was injurious, and ſhe grew worſe upon it; ſoon after, a Stupor or Paralytic numbneſs ſeiſed her: To be ſhort, ſhe was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my care and management; I ſent her three Anti-ſcorbutick Medicines, namely, my Scorbute-Pills, <hi>Elixir,</hi> and Sudorific Extract to be uſed in that order and method as the Medicines and her Condition required: at the months end ſhe gained the uſe of her Limbs, but were ſomething weak; yet no pains as formerly: and upon the uſe of the Sudorific Extract, ſome ſpots were driven forth, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Scurvy did appear and ſatisfied them more fully, what I had determined of her diſeaſe: The Winter being very ſharp, did ſometimes interrupt her Courſe, and retarded the compleating of a Cure, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33861:26"/>elſe might have been finiſhed in a ſhorter time. At the beginning of <hi>March</hi> I ſet her into the ſame Courſe again, which was diligently obſerved; and in <hi>April</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe was perfectly reſtored: In the Courſe of theſe Medicines (according to the Account received) I obſerved her pains to leſſen and ceaſe upon the uſe of the Sudorific Extract, and not before; which Medicine chiefly reſtored her the uſe of her Limbs; and it was reaſon to expect, the greateſt benefit, as to that particular in the Caſe, ſhould acrue from a Diaphore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic Medicine; that ſearching and penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the habite of the Body, by tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and breathing Sweats ſhould diſſodg and diſcuſſe the Scorbutic Matter which infeſted the Nerves and Muſcles, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and diſabling the parts in their Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Action.</p>
            <p>By ſuch Examples as this, and other different Caſes as to the Symptoms, yet parallel with it as to the parts affected and Morbiſic Cauſe; I was fully ſatisfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that a Sudorific Medicine was of neceſſary uſe in many Scorbutic Caſes, and without which, a Cure could not be performed; I therefore prepared a Medicine that might effectually anſwer the ſcope of that inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which might operate by Tranſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33861:26"/>and gentle ſweating, and, by a kindly aſſiſting of Nature in that operation, might depurate the whole Maſſe of blood, and free the habite of the body from any Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butic Impurity and Degenerate Matter, which at certain ſeaſons of the year, and by accidental promoting Cauſes, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and produceth various internal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers and Diſeaſes, Scorbutic Feavers, continual and intermitting Quotidian, Tertian and Quartan, Head-aches, and Pains in ſeveral parts, Pleuriſies, Aſthma's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or external and Cutany-Difedations; as Spots, Scurff, Scabs, Puſtul's, Tettars, Ringworms, Tumors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And becauſe our blood, eſpecially in theſe Northern Climates, doth abound with a <hi>ſeroſa Colluvies,</hi> a Seroſity or Superfluous wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery humor; a good Sudoriſic Medicine is of great uſe; for when this ſerous matter abounds and increaſe the ther by the inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Attraction &amp; Separation of the Reins, that ſhould expend and drain it; or the Pores ſhut up, and Trauſpiration de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that ſhould inſenſibly exhauſt it, doth then by Preternatural Retention de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and change its Nature and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; that which was mild turns acid, ſharp and moleſting; and variouſly dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating doth cauſe ſeveral Diſeaſes and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33861:27"/>Pains in divers parts of the Body as it Circulates in the Veſſels; or extravaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and wandring about being expulſed from part to part as hoſtile and injurious) by the ſtrength and fortitude of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> or innate ſpirit that inhabits as the Life-guard in each part of the body.</p>
            <p>This Sudoriſic Medicine prepared for the purpoſes aforeſaid. I appoint in all Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butic Caſes, requiring Tranſpiration or Sweating; and I find great ſucceſs in the uſe of it (eſpecially being now much alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and improved) Many Diſeaſes are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed by Sudorificks, that purgatives can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail againſt; the reaſon is this; Firſt, becauſe ſome Diſeaſes do ariſe, and depend upon a flatulent Spirit or Meteor that is generated in the body; and theſe Diſeaſes are more accute and dangerous, than others, becauſe their matter is more active, ſubtile, and of ſuddain motions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Nature of a Spirit, is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrative and irreſiſtible in its motion; as Apoplexy, Epilepſy, hiſterical Paſſions, Peſtilential Seminaries, ſuddain Swoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which do not yield Obedience to Purgatives, being of a more ſubtile ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous nature, is not ejected by Vomit, or Stool as groſſer Morbific Humours are; but requires a Medicine equivalent and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33861:27"/>proportionate to their Nature; that is, pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trative, ſubtile and acute in Operation, proper to diſcuſs, evaporate, and tranſpire. Secondly, many Diſeaſes though ariſing from groſſer and humoral cauſes, that would obey the Power and Virtue of Purgatives; yet by reaſon they are lodged in the habit of the body and more exterior parts, are out of diſtance and beyond the reach and ſphere of their activity: but a good Sudorific penetrates and ſearcheth all parts, raiſeth the Seminaries, and enters the ſecret Dormitories of lurking Diſeaſes, and gives them expulſion by its ſubtil Operation and acute Power: and here I remember the condition of a Patient which I will relate to you, pertinent to the preſent diſcourſe. A young gentlewoman of a fair Complexion and very clear skin, by Melancholy (and other cauſes) was much altered and become brown, muddy, and diſcoloured in particular places; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a Scurf did ariſe and ſome Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples here and there, which was troubleſome by itching: this Gentlewoman was let blood and purged often, but ſtill her trouble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained: then ſhe was adviſed to a Waſh to clear the skin, and to take away the heat and pimples; which did take effect in a few daies, but upon retiring of this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33861:28"/>inwards, ſhe fell deſperately ſick, with violent pains in her head, and ready to faint away often. Hereupon I was ſent for, and examined the whole matter; and finding the acuteneſs of her ſickneſs to ariſe from an imprudent repelling of a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and forcing it back upon Nature, which ſhe had brought forth to the skin; I immediately appointed her a Doſe of my ſudorific Extract to be given her, which put her into a breathing Sweat; and when the Medicine had done its Operation, her pains and ſickneſs were almoſt gone: the next day I appointed another Doſe to be given her, to ſweat gently for two or three hours, and before the Operation of the Medicine was ſpent, her pain and ſickneſs quite left her; and then appeared ſome of the former Symptoms again upon the skin, but without itching. The preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of her ſickneſs being over, I cauſed her to reſt two or three daies, and gave her an <hi>Elixir</hi> to take every day, to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Nature and recover her ſtrength: then ſhe fell to the Sudorific Extract a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to cleanſe the Blood, and to breathe out that impurity which was lodged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the skin; with convenient intermſſion ſhe repeated this Sudorific Medicine three or four times more, and then the former
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33861:28"/>Symptoms quite left her, and ſhe regained her former beauty and clearneſs of skin. By this you may underſtand, that a Sudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rific Medicin ſome times is effectual, when Purgatives cannot prevail; yet 'tis injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Nature, to draw back again what ſhe hath protruded and brought forth to the Circumference of the Body: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that rely and inſiſt too much upon Purging, thinking to cleanſe the whole Body by that Operation only, are much deceived: Purging is good but not alwaies; other Medicines muſt come in and take their place, according as the caſe requires: Purging cleanſeth the Center, but Sudorificks purifie the exterior parts.</p>
            <p>That you may know when a Sudorific Medicine is required as neceſſary, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to the Cure, I'le tell you in what caſes I appoint this Sudorific Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to be taken: In curing the Scurvy, I find good ſucceſs thereby, to cleanſe and purifie the Blood that is degenerate and vitiated with a Scorbutic taint and impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: or when the Pores are occluded and imperſpirable, the Body tumified and puft up for want of tranſpiration and ventila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when pricking pains or itching in the fleſh moleſt and trouble, by a ſaline or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crid Seroſity extravaſated, and erratick;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33861:29"/>when ſpots, tumors, puſtul's, ſcurfe, pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or ſuch like appear upon any part of the Body: This Sudorific Medicine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſeth and diſcipates the confluence of Humours teſorting to any part, opens the Pores, tranſpires and drives out the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentions matter, congeſted and lodged under the skin: alſo when a Laſſitude or wearineſs poſſeſs the Limbs; when the ſpirits are torpid, dull heavy (as it is the caſe of many Scorbutic perſons) being alienated from their purity and wonted vigour, by a degenerate and depraved ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ſuccus, cloging and ſettering them, that ſhould ſupport and maintain them with an addiſional ſupply of a congenerous extraction; in this caſe a good Sudorific is the beſt relief, to depurate the Vital ſtream, and alimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary liquors of the Body, from whence the Spirits receive ſtrength and vigour again.</p>
            <p>The Doſe, and Circumſtances that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the taking of this Sudoific Extract is thus: to a man or woman of a weak ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der body; at firſt I give a dram and half, the next time two drams, but ſtronger bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies give two drams at the firſt doſe, then two drams and half, almayes begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a leſſer doſe; and encreaſe the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33861:29"/>quantity, as from the quantity of a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg to a Cheſtunt, according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and ſtrength of the body after try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: Firſt, becauſe there is great difference in bodyes, ſome require more; as hard, dry bodyes and thicker skinns, being more difficult to tranſpire; and ſome leſs, as tender, moiſt bodyes, of a rare Texture, and open Pores, more apt to breath out. Secondly, Nature is better pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome Medicines gradually, then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a full doſe at firſt; if Nature takes a diſguſt to a Medicine, ſhe ſeldom agrees with it after,
<note place="margin">à leviori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, &amp; procede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ad for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiora, eſt ordo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientum.</note> though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good: therefore at the firſt begin with a little doſe (for tryal) though the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine be very amicable, and the next time you may encreaſe, and take a little more.</p>
            <p>The manner of taking is thus, Roll it in a little Sugar, and ſwallow it down.</p>
            <p>Take it at Night (having eaten but a little Spoon-meat for your Supper) in Bed covered warm; and a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour after, drink a draught of Roſemary-Poſſet, or Mace-Ale, then you may ſleep as you find your ſelf diſpoſed. Or you may take this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33861:30"/>in a Morning very early, after the ſame manner, and lye in Bed half that day, ſleep if you will, that does not check the Medicine, you will have the benefit of Tranſpiration in your ſleep: <hi>Somnus Cohibet omnem evacuationem preter Sudorem aph.</hi> nor are you to expect great Sweats, but only moiſt Breathings, not at all troubleſome.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps being too haſty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to effect their Cure, may think one or two great Sweats may do as much good as half a dozen gentle breathings,
<note place="margin">Saepius mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movere, melius eſt quam Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedando viresproſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternere.</note> and ſo ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the time of their Cure; but I cannot approve that Courſe, to impair Nature by violent and large Exhauſtions; you thereby fruſtrate the benefit of the Medicine, which rightly uſed, will prove very ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the purpoſes appointed. This Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorific Extract may be taken twice in a week, on the intermitting dayes when you do not purge, having firſt taken three doſes of the Scorbute Pills to cleanſe the ſtomack and bowels, before you begin to Sweat, that the groſſer matter and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe parts be not driven into the habit of the body. For going abroad, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33861:30"/>this, if you take the Sudorific in the Morning, you muſt not go out that day, the Pores being open: but if you take it over night, the weather not cold and ſearching, but temperate or hot; you may go forth next day, if your diſeaſe, ſtrength, and condition of body admit.</p>
            <p>Thoſe perſons that uſe the three Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorbutic Medicines before mentioned, do obſerve this order, except in ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Caſes, and complicated Diſeaſes, by particular advice: Firſt, they begin with the Scorbute-Pills to cleanſe the Center of the Body, as the Stomack, Guts, Meſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Liver, and Spleen: The next day and all the intermitting days between Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they uſe the <hi>Elixir,</hi> to ſtrengthen the declining Faculties and rectifie the Digeſtions: and after three doſes of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Pills taken, they begin with the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorifick Medicine, to purifie the Blood, and cleanſe the habit of the Body; and theſe are to be uſed twice in a week, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding alſo with the other Medicines in their turns as before. But now you are come to uſe the Sudorifick Extract, you may take the Scorbutic Pills but once in the week, whereas before you took them once in four or five days; this is my courſe and practice in curing the Scurvy and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33861:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:33861:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:33861:32"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Canons of Art, is alſo verified by much experience to be moſt effectual.</p>
            <p>The chief reaſon why I am ſo large here, in the general uſe of theſe Medicines is to avoid the daily trouble of directions in writing to each particular Patient, except there be good cauſe.</p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed what I propoſed in my ſelf to make Publick: The Nature, of this ſpreading Diſeaſe the Scurvy; its va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Symptoms and appearance, that it may be known though in a various dreſs and diſguiſe; the uſual complicated affects that aſſociate and attend it; its internal eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Cauſes, manner of Generation, and ſeat of Radication in the Body, the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal procuring and promoting Cauſes; the chief indications ſo Cure; three Anti-ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butic Medicines laid down as exemplars, anſwering the ſcope of thoſe curative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; and ſome remarkable Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Practice; And this is the ſumm of the whole Work.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33861:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
